So today, we're going to
talk about evaluation.
So far in this class
we've done everything we
need to train a language model.
We defined the architecture,
the optimizer, the main training
loop.
We showed how to make the
training fast with kernels,
parallelism.
And then we saw scaling laws.
We saw a little bit of how to
make inference fast as well.
So the only missing piece
now is talking about the data
that you train on.
So we're going to spend next
week talking about that.
And data is going to
shape the model behavior.
If you train on
code, then presumably
your model is going
to be good at code.
If you train only
on DNA sequences,
it probably can't speak English.
But before we even
get to data, we
need to talk about what
behavior we want from a model,
and that's going to be
the topic of evaluation.
So evaluation asks a
very simple question--
given the model that we've
trained, how good is it?
So what is good?
So evaluation might seem like
a fairly mechanical process.
You define some
prompts, you send
these prompts to your model,
you get back some responses,
and then you compute
the accuracy.
So why do we have a whole
lecture on evaluation?
But actually, evaluation
is a very deep topic,
and it's also very important
because evaluation is what
shapes the development of AI.
Evaluation sets North Stars
and model developers--
open, closed-- everyone
looks at evaluation
as a measure of progress.
So by thinking carefully
about your evaluation,
you implicitly shape
the development
of what your model is
going to be able to do.
So what's hard about
evaluation is the following.
So often, you start it with
an abstract construct of what
do I want my model to do?
Maybe I want my model to
be good at conversation
or good at reasoning.
OK.
So those are abstract concepts.
And then evaluation
is really the process
of turning that into a concrete
metric powered by, presumably,
some concrete prompts
or environments.
So this is going to
be the core challenge,
and we'll see many
examples of how
this process of abstract
construct, concrete metric
shows up.
So let's go back to a question
of what makes a model good.
Just kind of superficially.
Maybe a model is good if
it does well on benchmarks.
So there's this website,
Artificial Analysis,
which has become a bit of a
standard for thinking about
quote unquote,
"intelligence of models."
So if you go to
Artificial Analysis AI,
you can see a ranking of
different models from GPT-5.5,
all the way down-- well, there's
many more models after this
point.
And so this is a measure.
It includes a bunch of different
data sets, some of which
we'll talk about.
Or maybe a model is good if
it does well on benchmark
and is also cheap to run,
because cost should matter.
And this plot shows both
the intelligence index
from before, but
against how much money
it costs to run a particular
model based on inference cost.
And you can see, of course,
as you might expect,
that the two are correlated.
The more you pay to run, the
higher the intelligence index,
but it's not exactly aligned.
But maybe a model is good
if people just prefer it.
Later we'll also go a
little bit more into depth.
So this is the take that
Arena AI, formerly known
as Chatbot Arena, takes.
And you can form a
ranking based on models,
based on whether
people like it or not.
Or maybe a model is
good if people simply
choose to use it, and
therefore, pay for it.
So OpenRouter is
this service that
allows one to use
multiple different models
through a central endpoint.
And as a result,
they collect a lot
of statistics of what
models people are using.
And they publish
statistics, which
is really interesting
to look at,
the top bottles that are
used through OpenRouter.
So now, this is not
representative of all model
usage, but it gives you a sense
of what people on open router
are doing.
And so this is kind of
more of an economic lens.
I don't what good is, but
if people are paying for it,
it must be good.
OK.
So none of those are
necessarily the correct answer.
I don't know If there
is a correct answer,
but I'm just trying to get you
to think about different ways
of thinking about what good is.
So let's start now by looking at
different ways, concrete ways,
of evaluating language models.
And there's no better place
to start than going back
to the core idea of a
language model, which
is that it's a distribution P
of x over sequences of tokens.
And through that lens,
there's a very natural way
to evaluate a
distribution, which
is a perplexity, or
likelihood or log loss.
Those are all kind
of related concepts.
And it basically says, I
have a test data set d,
and I'm going to see how much
probability mass my language
model assigns to that d.
And I normalize it and
divide so that the numbers
are more interpretable.
But that's basically it.
How much mass does my
probability language model
assigned to a data set.
OK, so this is fairly natural.
In fact, when we
were doing training,
we minimized the perplexity
on the training set.
So the obvious thing to do
is measure the perplexity
on the test set, and this is
what people traditionally did
in language modeling research
for many years throughout
the 2010s.
If you pick up a
language modeling paper,
this is what they did.
And back then,
standard data sets
included the Penn
Treebank, WikiText-103.
There was also this One
Billion Word Benchmark,
which was taken from
machine translation sources.
And this is all in the
classic paradigm, which is
in-distribution of evaluation.
You train on some train
split of that data set,
and then you evaluate on some
test split of that data set.
And people actually
made a lot of progress,
which was just measured
in perplexity reduction.
So for example, there's
this famous paper
from 2016, which
showed that you could
apply CNNs and LSTMs to this
One Billion Word Benchmark
and get a huge
perplexity reduction.
And bear in mind,
around that time,
people were talking still
about n-gram models and maybe
hybrid models.
And this was the first
definitive result
that showed just pure neural
is clearly the way to go.
OK, so life was very
simple back then.
You train on the train split.
You test on a test
split for perplexity.
So then when GPT-2 came
around in 2019 from OpenAI,
they trained on
the data set called
WebText, which was 40
gigabytes of text websites
that were linked from Reddit.
And the way they evaluated
was actually different.
They evaluated zero-shot
on standard data sets
that everyone else
was evaluating on.
So this is out-of-distribution
evaluation.
So this is a table from their
paper, which show that as they
train different models.
So the biggest model is
1.5 billion parameters.
And they were able to show
quite a bit of improvement,
especially on the
small data sets.
So for example, PTB,
which is a tiny data set.
They were getting 35 perplexity
compared to the State
of The Art, which is 46.
Now, if you have enough
in-distribution data,
you don't quite do
as well as the SOTA.
But nonetheless, this
is kind of impressive,
given that this model was not
trained on One Billion Word's
data set at all.
I don't know.
Maybe there was some
overlap, because I
don't know if they did a
careful train test decontam.
And so it ushered
in a new paradigm
of thinking about language
models as not just
the in-distribution
setting, but how
we wanted to train
on a large data set
and evaluate on standard
benchmarks, which nowadays I
think has been very
common standard.
But back then, it was seen
as a bit of a novelty.
I will also argue, since we're
talking about perplexity, that
perplexity is you all need.
I wouldn't to take
this too seriously,
but I think it is
a mindset, I think,
that drives a lot of
language modeling research.
And the basic argument
goes like this.
So there's some true
distribution out there--
let's call it t--
and you're training
this model p.
So what is the best
perplexity you could obtain?
Well, the best
perplexity is the entropy
of that true
distribution, and that
is realized when p equals t.
So by minimizing
perplexity, you're basically
pushing down the perplexity.
And the only unique minimizer
is when you actually
get the true distribution.
And when you have the true
distribution, you're done.
You just model everything.
You can solve all
the problems, and you
can do things like
condition on the problem,
generate a solution.
You can condition on a
question, generate the answer.
So by pushing down
on perplexity,
we'll eventually reach
AGI, is the argument.
I mean, this might
sound, I don't know,
either a bit fantastical.
But in some sense,
this is really,
I think, a strong
driver of many people
who have been scaling and
scaling language models
at a time when, maybe, the
gains weren't as obvious.
Before GPT-3, I
think it wasn't clear
that language models were going
to have such a huge impact.
And it was really this belief
that, if you drove perplexity
down, good things will happen.
So of course, Perplexity
is maybe not all.
And one way to frame it is
that perplexity is maybe more
than you need.
So for example, if you have
a sentence like "Stanford was
founded in 1885,"
perplexity will say,
penalize the prediction
on all tokens.
So in particular, it'll say,
what is the probability of 1885,
given the rest?
And that token is
probably pretty useful.
It's basically a Q&A example,
phrased as sentence completion.
So it captures knowledge
about the world.
But other ones-- for example,
the first word of a sentence,
or even "founded"--
maybe not that
interesting, I think.
And perplexity doesn't care.
It's going to charge you bits
for every bit of a deviation
from the true distribution.
So there is a bit
of a solution here,
which is you can always measure
the conditional perplexity.
You can condition
on some prompt,
and then you can measure the
perplexity of the remaining
response.
So that allows you
to, in general,
focus on certain
tokens that you believe
to be relevant
and less on others
that are sort of incidental.
OK.
And also, it's
important to remember
that some benchmarks, even
though they are not explicitly
a perplexity
measure, are actually
just perplexity in disguise.
So, for example, if you
think about closed tasks.
There's this lambada paper
from, actually, a while ago,
2016, which is basically
fill in the blank.
And you have a context,
you have a sentence.
"Do you honestly think I will
want you to have a blank."
And the goal is to
figure out that word.
And even though this is
measured in terms of accuracy,
it is really a next-token
prediction problem.
And here, it's not
perplexity of all the words,
it's carefully chosen.
If you read this paper,
it's really carefully chosen
to be words, such
that you actually need
a bunch of long-contexts
to resolve.
So this is actually something
that the early GPT papers really
latched on to because they
were interested in long-context
modeling, thinking that
that was a key to unlocking
reasoning and all these things.
And really, by
focusing on positions
where, to resolve
that, it requires
long-distance
dependencies, is a way
to sharpen the perplexity
to some phenomenon
that you care about.
Here's another
popular classic data
set that you see in some
language modeling vowels.
HellaSwag.
So what is HellaSwag?
They went to various different
data sets and sources,
and came up with--
it's multiple choice,
but it's really
sentence completion.
And at some level,
it's perplexity.
So here's a sentence.
"A woman is outside
with a bucket and a dog.
The dog is running around.
She blank."
And then you're trying
to fill in which
sentence completes it the best.
So it's not exactly perplexity,
it's multiple choice.
But in some ways,
it's perplexity.
So one word of warning.
If you ever decide that
you're sold on perplexity
as, really, the
measure and you're
going to launch a leaderboard
and have people compete
against perplexity,
just a word of caution
is that, what is a perplexity
leaderboard look like?
So people are going to submit
a language model to you,
and you have to
compute a logprob.
You send them the test data, and
they give you back a logprob.
Well, you look at
that and say, hmm,
that might be a little
bit fishy because you
need to trust that the
probabilities they hand back
to you are valid and
that they sum to 1.
Otherwise, I could
just have implement LM,
and it always returns 1
or, I guess, logprob 0.
And I would get very
good perplexity,
but clearly, that's not
a valid distribution.
And so with this
contract it's not
really easy to check
that someone is actually
internally having
a log probability,
so there's some trust.
Maybe you have to look
at the code or something.
For downstream tasks, this
is much more straightforward
because you can
have a black box LM.
I give you a prompt,
you give me a response,
and I can just use that response
and calculate some accuracy.
So perplexity is
fundamentally different
because it deals
with distributions,
and you have to
be a bit careful.
And not to mention,
there's lots of problems
with autoregressive models.
But if you have VAEs or there's
some models where you can't even
compute the distribution--
you can compute only a bound--
then you have to really actually
trust the math as well that this
is actually a valid bound.
OK.
So The summary of perplexity
is that it is actually
still used quite heavily in
language model development.
It has some nice properties.
We saw that it's generally
used for scaling laws
because it's also
smoothly varying
with scale, which is important
for getting scaling laws.
But, at the end of the day,
especially if you're not
a believer, then you need some
benchmarks to really capture
real world situations,
to convince people
that your language
model is good.
For the believers, if I show you
a remarkably slow perplexity,
they'll be convinced.
OK, any questions
about perplexity?
OK.
Hopefully, everyone's
a believer now.
OK, so let's talk
about exam benchmarks.
So exams, as all of
your students know,
is a way that we
use to test humans.
And so you can adopt
the same mentality
to test language models.
The nice thing about
exams is that you
have a very careful
control over the subject,
over the difficulty.
You can design them to have
unambiguous correct answers,
which makes them easy to grade.
So there's a lot of nice
properties about exams.
And so, for this reason, a
lot of LM benchmarking culture
was based on just
this idea of exams.
So obviously, there's
been a lot of benchmarks,
but I'll just highlight
some of the ones
that I think have
been influential
in the development
of language models.
So this one is MMLU, or Massive
Multitask Language Understanding
from Hendrycks et al, 2020.
And at that time,
it wasn't clear
that language models were
really like general purpose task
solvers.
This was around the time
when GPT-3 came out.
Many people, I think, still
thought of language models
as, well, language models.
You generate fluent English.
But they had this
idea that, well,
let's just try to be
ahead of the curve here.
We're going to go
through 57 subjects,
we're going to have
a team of students
scour the internet
for different sources,
and really put together this
very comprehensive data set.
And despite the name MMLU,
which has the word Language
Understanding, it's
really about testing
knowledge and reasoning
and less so just
pure language understanding.
And the way they evaluated
it was with GPT-3,
using few-shot prompting.
So they essentially said,
I have formed this prompt.
The following are questions
about high school mathematics.
Some in-context examples of
question, answer, question,
answer, and then the final
question, and then the model
has to predict the answer.
So this seems very mundane.
But at that time
it was, I think,
pretty radical that
you would construct
this fairly complicated question
and with in-context examples
and everything, and
expect a language
model to actually do
something reasonable.
And sure enough, at the outset,
the models were not great,
I would say.
Some of the small models
were barely above chance.
And the larger
model-- this GPT-3--
was actually well above chance,
so this was kind of encouraging.
And then over the
years, as we know,
this benchmark has
essentially saturated.
So this is a site I don't think
this has all the data in it,
but about 3.5 Turbo.
This was like--
I guess, beginning of
2024-- oh, '23 actually--
to GPT-4.
And then, now it's in the 90s.
So there's also a
link you can follow up
later on, where you can
actually browse some
of the predictions of these
models, which is always
fun to see what models
actually goof up on
and what they get right.
OK.
So around 2024, when it
seemed like MMLU, there
was a lot of progress
made, it was like, OK--
you're going to see
this theme again--
OK, this benchmark
is getting too easy.
Let's try to make it harder.
Well, first of
all, they actually
noticed that there was some
noisy and trivial problems,
so let's get rid of them.
Four choices might be
a little bit too easy,
so let's expand that to 10.
At that point, it was much more
in vogue to use chain of thought
to solve these benchmarks,
whereas when GPT-3 came out,
that wasn't really a thing.
And it's clear that
some of these questions
could benefit from a
few reasoning steps.
So this new
benchmark was harder.
So now the accuracy of
the model is back at 33.
But as you can maybe
see from the progress
so far it started low.
And now it's back to I guess
it's like 88 almost 90, OK.
So this benchmark might be a
little bit too easy as well.
OK, so there's another
benchmark called
GPQA, which stands
for Google-Proof QA.
And the idea here is
that OK, how can we
get a really good benchmark?
And the idea is that, well,
if you can solve a problem
by looking at Google.
Google has the internet
and a language model
is trained on the internet.
So if you can just solve it
then that's probably too easy.
So they got some now PhD level.
So I think MMLU was
think about as actually--
maybe some of these were like
undergrad but maybe grad level.
But now, it's more explicitly
about questions that
are meant to be pretty hard.
And at this point
now you say, OK,
how do I come up with
really hard questions?
You actually have to go through
quite a bit of human labor
to get really hard questions.
So this was 61 PhD
contractors from Upwork.
Someone writes a question.
It goes through an expert
validation which then provides
feedback on the questions.
And then the question writer
goes and revises the question.
And another expert
looks at the question.
And then you have the question.
And then you send it
to some non-experts
who are given Google access.
And then you see if they
can solve the question.
So there's a subset of these
questions called the DIAMOND set
that you might see in
people's leaderboards
where if the two experts agree
and at one of the non-experts
is able to answer the question,
then that's deemed a good kind
of DIAMOND question.
So this is pretty
rigorous review process.
And PhD experts were
only able to get 65%.
So this is I think mostly
four-way multiple choice.
So this is above random.
But this is not a good grade if
you're getting 65% on an exam.
And it's not experts, even if
they had 30 minutes with access
to Google, they were getting a
bit over chance, but not much.
And at that point
GPT-4 was like 39%,
and let's see how
it's doing now.
So GPQA is now again 94.
So these benchmarks have a shelf
life of not too high I guess.
I will say that some
of these benchmarks,
even though they saturate
the larger models,
they're still useful
for developing
smaller models or fitting
scaling laws and so on.
So then, yeah.
How do you know that
when these tests are
being used for training
and actually your models
are communicating with these?
Yeah, so this is a very
important question.
So how do you know that
these questions aren't
just in the training set?
So the short answer is we
don't know because I don't know
what's in the training set.
I'll come back to
this contamination
point a little bit later
and ways of addressing it.
But you should always--
I'm glad you asked this.
You should always
take these numbers
with a little bit of a grain of
salt, because it's only trust.
Maybe just to say one more.
I think train contamination
is a little bit subtle.
Because it's probably
not the case that
they literally train on the set.
But questions can be
derived from other sources.
And those sources
could be trained on.
So often contamination is
a much more subtle process
than literally accidentally
training on the test.
Was there another question?
Same question.
OK, great.
Good always good
to be skeptical.
OK, so the final exam
benchmark I'll talk about
is something ominously
called Humanity's Last Exam.
This is from last year.
And they were saying,
OK, well these models
are getting so good.
Let's just give it
all we can to create
something that's really tough.
So this is multimodal,
many subjects.
It's still multiple choice.
And I guess some short answer.
So this was crowdsourced.
They had some money to
incentivize people who were
into money to create questions.
They also incentivize
with authorship
for those who are into that.
And they went through
multiple stages of reviews
filtered by frontier models.
There's a whole process.
Another answer to your question
is that they also held out
a private set that was
not released publicly,
so that they could make
sure that this did not
enter training.
And then you just
hope that the APIs
that you-- because you still
have to send this to the model,
that those prompts don't
end up in the training.
But let's hope that's the case.
So every data set
paper looks like this.
Previous benchmarks, look
the models are doing so well.
My data set, look all the
models are doing really poorly.
So this is a common pattern.
And this was especially
single digits.
It's pretty abysmal here.
And let's see how
we're doing in 2026.
So this one is-- it
still has some room.
So it's only at--
even Mythos is only at 64.7.
So this is indeed a pretty-- it
seems like a pretty hard exam.
OK, so to summarize this
section, as you can see,
we've trained it towards
harder and harder questions
as the models improve and we
saturate existing benchmarks.
It's interesting that multiple
choice format still survives
because it's--
with multiple
choice, I mean, you
can make it as
difficult as you want.
So some people think, well,
multiple choice is too easy.
Well, I mean, I can
give you a very hard
multiple-choice question.
That's not really the point.
I think more the point is
that multiple choice restricts
the set of questions
you can ask.
But in terms of difficulty, no
problem with multiple choice.
The main problem with
exam-based questions
is that this does not
capture real-world usage.
No one asks HLE questions
to a language model
except for when you're
evaluating on HLE.
Most of the time people are
asking open-ended questions.
They don't even necessarily
have a correct answer.
They might not be well
formed, and these benchmarks
do not capture that.
OK, so question.
How is the model output compared
with the ground truth answer?
So for HLE?
For accuracy, how is
the model's output
compared with the
ground truth answer,
to calculate the accuracy?
To calculate the accuracy
for how is the ground truth
compared.
So for multiple
choice, it's just like,
did you get the right answer?
So will we check the probability
distribution for each option
or how is--
So the language
model generates C.
And my answer is either
B or C or A or D,
and I just check if
they're the same or not.
So we are only
generating one token?
Yes, well, OK.
So then the question is
less about evaluation.
But how does the model
generate an answer?
So there's a few options.
One is that you generate--
literally you sample and
it generates a letter.
Or more commonly now you
generate a chain of thought.
You generate the answer
maybe some explanation.
But there is a way of extracting
an answer which does matter.
And language model evaluations
can be very sensitive to that
but I'm not going to
talk about that here.
So let's talk about a very
different class of benchmarks
called chat benchmarks.
So far we've talked about
multiple-choice tasks.
So they're still pretty good
at capturing some notion
of intelligence and difficulty.
But most people don't ask a
multiple-choice exam question
to their AI assistant
unless they're
trying to use their AI system
to do their exam for them,
which you would never.
One does that.
OK, so here's an example
semi-inspired by a real world
use case.
So I might say I want to make
a beet salad with cheese.
What herbs would work well
and what wouldn't work well?
OK, so this is a very
open-ended question.
And then you get some
response, which is, again,
an open-ended response.
And then the question is, how
do you evaluate this thing?
You can't just check
exact match with equality.
There's no ground truth even.
So there's a few ideas here.
We can go through them.
So one of the ideas was
pioneered by this Chatbot Arena.
And the idea is, well,
you ask humans, OK.
But the way they ask humans,
I think is a clever idea.
So they basically had
this set of this website
where any random person from
the internet can go in and chat.
And then instead of
a normal as assistant
in getting one
response, you actually
get two responses from
two different models
which are anonymized, and then
they rate which one is better.
So for example, you
put in this response,
you get these two, assistant A,
assistant B. And then you ask,
A is better, both are good,
both are bad, B is better?
So using this
process, you can get
a bunch of pairwise comparison
data of model A, model B, which
one is better?
And then you can use this
to compute ELO rankings
based on this.
So I don't know how many of
you are familiar with this
but just get everyone
on the same page.
In these ELO rankings, you
define your rating model
as a probability of a
particular model being
another [INAUDIBLE] model
as some function of the ELO
scores of model B and model A.
So the larger model ELO score
of A is the higher
the probability.
So it's a smooth mapping.
And then you fit this
model with the parameters,
which are the ELO
ratings to maximize
the probability of the
pairwise comparisons, OK.
And then as a
result, you basically
get a rating for
each of your models.
OK, so this is what Chatbot
Arena nowadays known
as Arena AI did.
And you can get
this nice ranking.
I guess Claude Opus is
doing pretty well here
but some other models
are on the list as well.
OK.
So there's a few things that
are nice about this setup.
One is that you have
real-world prompts.
So the idea is that anyone
can come to the site,
and the incentive for
someone to come to the site
is that they get free
access to a language model.
And so there's this
implicit assumption
that they're actually trying to
use it to do something useful.
And therefore you get
a real-world prompt.
But one thing you should keep in
mind is, who are these people?
Random person on
the internet is--
I don't know what
that distribution.
Random person on the internet
who comes to La Marina.
I don't know what that
distribution looks like.
I think in their paper,
they have some demographics,
but demographics don't
tell the whole story.
You could worry about
different biases coming
from the different models.
Maybe spammers.
People are trying to game, who
maybe even submitted a model
and they want their
model to look good.
You just don't know.
It's a little bit
of a Wild West.
There's another issue which
is that the binary preference,
which is better, A or B
is very nice and simple
and feeds into this rating,
but does conflate style
and correctness.
So ELO ratings for chess
makes a lot of sense,
because the only thing that
matters is, did you win?
But which one is better
is much less clear cut.
And there's questions of
the human is the judge here.
The person who
puts in the prompt
is answering the question.
And this is good
because in some level,
because the person
has some intent
and they can declare whether
their intent was met.
To some extent,
except for they're
presumably asking the
question because they
don't know the answer.
So if I give you
two answers, how
are they to judge
which one is correct?
And then there's also the
problem of sycophancy,
where maybe more
pleasing answers
are going to be
upweighted highly compared
to correct but honest answers.
So there's a lot of
potential issues here.
But the nice thing
about this method, which
is that you don't
need to feed the same
prompts to all the models,
and this is the beauty of ELO.
In chess, you
don't have to play.
Everyone plays everyone else.
It can just be some
sparse sample of that.
And you can still
derive rankings as long
as the graph is connected.
And this is important
because human is rating
and you can't expect a
human to rate all the models
or even more than two models.
And the nice thing
as well is that
as new prompts and
new models come in,
there's a natural story for
making this updating over time.
So let me talk about
a different approach.
So this is AlpacaEval from 2023.
There were some instructions
derived from various sources.
And the metric here is the win
rate against a baseline model.
So you have a model,
AlpacaEval says,
I'm going to generate
it for a prompt,
generate using let's
say baseline model GPT-4
preview at that time and then
judge using GPT preview, which
one is better?
So immediately, this raises
a question of potential bias.
But let's put that
aside for now.
So this is basically
an instantiation
of LLM as a judge, which
is very popular these days
for evaluating language models.
And you can mitigate
this bias by having
multiple judges and ensembling
and so on and so forth.
So one problem with
initial AlpacaEval
is that LLM judges
favor long responses.
And this led to a bunch
of leaderboard gaming
where a bunch of models that
were fine tuned were submitted
and they got really
high LLM AlpacaEval
performance just because
the responses were longer.
So this got fixed in a
subsequent paper where
the use a very simple regression
method to de-bias the metric.
OK, but this raises a more
general question here,
which is not necessarily
specific to AlpacaEval which is,
how do you evaluate a metric?
So we've been talking
about evaluation of models.
And if I have a metric, how
you can evaluate a model.
But if I'm coming
up with a metric,
how do this metric is any good?
So this is a hard problem.
And there's no answer here.
One thing you can do is
more of a sanity check
is you can look at
correlation with other metrics
with the idea that higher isn't
necessarily better in all cases
unless you are trying to
mimic this other metric.
So AlpacaEval correlation
with Chatbot Arena
is 0.98 which is quite high.
So which suggests
that you could--
let's say you wanted to
evaluate on a Chatbot Arena,
but you're too shy
to put your model
or you don't want to wait
for humans or whatever,
you can use AlpacaEval
to evaluate instead.
Now, this correlation,
of course,
is with respect to a
certain set of models.
And so this might
not hold for models
that let's say are stronger
than GPT-4 preview.
So at this point, this
leaderboard I don't think
is really--
hasn't been maintained
in over a year but this
is what it looked
like at that time.
So there's another
benchmark I'll talk about,
which is WildBench and this one
was sourced a bunch of examples
from human-chatbot
conversations.
So like Chatbot Arena, they
also put up a free service
where people could
chat with this bot
and they collected the queries.
And then like AlpacaEval,
they used LLM as a judge
to evaluate the model.
The main innovation
here is the use
of a checklist,
which is generated
and specific to a
particular prompt or task.
And the idea here
is that if you just
ask a language model to judge
whether this response is good
or not.
This is in some sense a
very ill-defined task.
I don't know what depends
on what you care about.
And so the idea here is that
by having a checklist or some
of rubric, this greatly scopes
and makes the task evaluation
task more well-defined.
So they did this, also,
they showed correlation
with Chatbot Arena
which admittedly
is a little bit circular because
then you can ask why, well,
is Chatbot Arena really
the ground truth?
But at least we're all in
the same boat together.
OK, so to conclude this
section, how do you
evaluate open-ended responses?
There's no clear solution
here but there's some ideas.
Pairwise comparisons between a
reference and a model response
is generally a good
idea because especially
for very similar
responses, you can
give directional information.
Well, this one's slightly
better than this.
But in terms of absolute ranking
like is this a 7 out of 10
or a 8 out of 10?
That tends to be a
lot less high signal.
One should always
be aware of biases
both in terms of
humans or LLM judges.
They have different biases,
but nonetheless that's
something important
to pay attention to.
Perhaps the only thing
you might be able to do
is you evaluate over
multiple judges, humans,
and judges of all
everything is saying
your model is better than--
maybe your model is better.
And finally, the
evaluation problem here
of open-ended response.
I would emphasize is
not really well-defined.
And so increasingly,
I think it's
important to define rubrics
or checklists to improve
the reliability or
well-definedness
of an actual evaluation.
And this is true regardless
of a human and a judge.
So anyone who's
done crowdsourcing
knows that if you just
ask a human to rate
something without
giving some of rubric,
you're probably going to get
very nonsensical results.
OK, so let's move on
to the agentic world.
So you can think
about what we've
been doing so far is evaluate
what language models say,
and that's chat.
And now, we're going to evaluate
what LLMs do, which is agents.
And so for anyone who's
following AI hype,
agents are everywhere.
And these are--
definitely, I think
going to transform the way that
we think about language models.
So Agent is basically
a language model
plus some scaffold, which
is a logic for deciding
how the language model
is going to be called
and what tools it can has access
to and so on and so forth.
So there's a few benchmarks
I want to just point out
that are authentic.
So one is very popular.
It's just called SWE-bench.
Basically, the task
is you're given
a code base and a description
of a GitHub issue, submit a PR.
And the way you evaluate a PR is
whether it passes the unit test.
So these tests are designed so
that before you submit a PR,
certain unit tests don't pass.
And then your goal is to fix it.
So certain unit tests pass and
you don't break anything else.
So here's an example
of some instructions.
Here's the issue.
And then some code that is
provided in the context.
And then your goal is
to generate a patch.
And given a patch
you are evaluated on
whether you pass or not.
So the good thing about
this is that the evaluation
is very straightforward.
And let's see how we're
doing on SWE-bench.
Actually, this is going to
be SWE-bench Verified which
later I'll show you, tell
you why this happened.
So SWE-bench in--
this was only I
guess 2024 was still around
16% and now it's up to 93.
Good job Mythos.
So this is a very canonical
generic benchmark,
as a lot of the
attention on agents
has been invested
in coding abilities.
So SWE-bench really
pioneered this way
of thinking about how to
assess an agent's ability
to write and code in a
realistic environment.
So here's another project
called Terminal-Bench.
And here the idea is
that this is going
to be more general purpose.
And we're going to basically
have the environment be
a computer terminal.
And we're going to
define a bunch of tasks
that can be done in
a computer terminal
by typing in a
bunch of commands.
And the nice thing
about this environment
is a very simple and universal.
And these tasks were
crowdsourced from 93 people
from across the world.
89 of these tasks are
constitute Terminal-Bench 2.0.
These tasks generally
take ranging from one hour
to over a week, depending
on whether you're
an expert or a junior.
And then, here's
what the leaderboard
looks like as of today.
So top models are
the frontier models.
One thing that's interesting is
that the agent is also important
here because you can have
two agents but the same model
and they have
different accuracies.
So another benchmark I'll
talk about is Cybersecurity.
So this is 40 Capture
The Flag tasks.
And the setting here
is that you have
an agent that is
given an environment
and it can run various commands
like look at the source code.
It can access the web server.
And the goal is to essentially
hack into this server
to extract some flag, which
is a unique string that
proves that you've
hacked into the server.
So these are competitions,
cybersecurity exercises that
are done by humans normally.
And this is an example
of what the agent
scaffold looks like here.
This is a very simplistic
version where basically you
have one continuous memory.
You produce some action, you
get environment feedback,
and then you put the
results into this buffer
and this is concatenated.
As I'll show you
later, this history
obviously grows quite a bit.
And you'll need to have better
ways of managing context.
So this is what the leaderboard
looks like when it came out.
The best models were
around 10% or so.
And over time now it's
completely solved actually.
So that's CyBench.
There's another
class of problems
which are MLE engineering.
So this benchmark has a
bunch of Kaggle competitions
which involve processing
data, training models,
and so on and so forth.
And the agent can look at the
data set, read the description,
write code, train models, and
you eventually submit something
and you get a grade.
So this is what the leaderboard
looks like right now.
And again, you can see that it's
really the same usual suspects
on the LLM side.
But there's quite
a bit of variation
in terms of the different
agent scaffolds.
So one thing to note
about, I'll point out
about agent scaffolds is
that they matter a lot.
So when I said I talk about
language model evaluation,
this is a broader than
language model evaluation.
And the reason is that unlike
what I mentioned before
with this earliest CyBench
agent scaffold, now
you have to be a lot more
sophisticated to solve
really complicated tasks.
One thing that people realize
is that explicit planning
is helpful.
You can't just stream
of consciousness,
chain of thought this.
And then you build
up this context
and the agent can easily
lose track of where it is.
So instead of keep a to-do
list, get it checked off.
Hierarchical delegation, agents
should call other sub-agents
with some clean context.
And that agent does some stuff
and returns only the result.
The master agent doesn't need
to see all the gory details,
and this can help encapsulate,
provide some encapsulation.
Memory, people have been
experimenting around
with explicitly reading
and writing files,
especially as the context grows.
You can't just store it
in your context window.
And then finally, there is more
context engineering in the style
of managing the process.
When should you
delegate to sub-agents?
When to try this strategy
versus this other strategy, what
to write persistent memory.
And these things are
generally optimized
for the particular
language model.
So agents are exciting because
they enhance the capability
surface of language models.
Scaffolds are very important.
So really, when we talk
about evaluating agents,
it's evaluating both
the language model
and the agent scaffold.
Now, we're going to
switch gears a little bit
and talk about this other very
different style of benchmarks.
I call them pure reasoning
for lack of a better term.
And the motivation is that
all the tasks so far require
some linguistic and
world knowledge.
And so the question
is, can we just
isolate reasoning or
pure fluid intelligence
from a knowledge
and knowing facts?
And you could argue
that this gives you
a form of more
pure intelligence.
So there was this
project, ARC-AGI,
which started back in 2019,
where the goal was exactly this.
So the task was meant to
be 100% solvable by humans,
but challenging for AIs.
And every task is a special
snowflake or that's the intent.
And so memorizing
a bunch of facts
or solving previous
problems shouldn't really
help you that much.
So if you guys are
remembering your LLM history,
2019 was pre-LLM.
I mean this was GPT-2 era.
So this was prescient
in that regard.
So here's an example of the
first iteration of that problem.
You're given these
pictures and you're
trying to guess what comes next.
And if you take 10 seconds, you
can probably solve this problem.
So you probably guess it's
to just fill in the yellow
to form the rectangle.
So then last year, there
was an updated version
of this task, which was
a bit more complicated.
And you can take a look at this.
So here's the trajectory.
So when ARC-AGI-1 came out--
I think this is actually 0.
So basically models
didn't do anything.
So there's GPT-3--
pre-trained model didn't
move the needle at all, right.
And this was exactly as
the creators had intended.
Pre-trained models
just learn what
the facts are on the
internet and maybe learn
linguistic patterns.
But none of that is
actually helpful directly,
at least for these
ARC-AGI tasks.
And then something
happened in 2024.
And this is when OpenAI
released their o1 and o3 models.
Then things started taking
off pretty abruptly.
And now, ARC-AGI-1
is basically solved.
And even around 2025
when ARC-AGI-2 came out,
this has also-- it's
not quite solved,
but it looks like it's on
its way to being solved.
So it was really the reasoning
capabilities that unlocked this.
And now one could wonder
whether all the knowledge
of actual pre-training was
necessary for this task.
And certainly,
without pre-training
we wouldn't have this
explosion of reasoning models.
So arguably it was
still important,
but not maybe directly
visible for much
of the history of ARC-AGI.
So now, just last month,
ARC-AGI-3 comes out.
So you see this
familiar pattern.
Our creators look at
this and it's like, oh,
time for a new benchmark.
So this is now an
interactive environment
where you can go online
and you can play this game.
So again, no language.
You're just trying to figure
out, based on patterns.
It's kind of fun.
And now the scores
are extremely low.
So next year when
I teach this class,
I'm sure I'll have
to update this slide.
But we'll see.
So I think this ARC-AGI
line is a really interesting
to think about.
The goal is to disentangle
reasoning from knowledge.
This is really hard to do.
And it's not--
I think this is probably
the best attempt at this.
It's not clear whether you can
really fully decouple things.
And certainly, if people really
cared about this benchmark,
I think people probably could--
people can benchmark I
think probably anything.
So you could design
questions like,
are these-- these still
come from some prior
and not sure there's anything as
quote unquote pure as reasoning.
This is also constrained
to human reasoning.
The explicit goal is to
be 100% human solvable
within some reasonable time.
So this doesn't really extend
to superhuman reasoning,
for example [INAUDIBLE]
winning more gold medals
or solving open math problems,
which arguably are still
very useful and important.
But clearly this exposes some
gaps in the current models.
So there is work to do if
you think about the goal
as basically being able
to solve all the tasks.
So this ARC-AGI-3 especially
looks quite graphic.
So is there some multimodal
content involved or encoding
or as a textual
representation as well?
Yeah so the question is
this looks very graphical.
And so what is the input
to a language model?
So this is essentially--
I don't know what the--
I think it's 64 by 64.
So you can provide
this image, or you
can provide it in Ascii Art or
some of textual representation.
Either way, there is
a spatial element here
that the model has to reason
about, which is really not
English or natural language.
So let's talk about
shift gears and talk
about another
class of benchmarks
which is related to safety.
So people have been
talking about safety
in language models for a while.
And if you think about
other areas such as cars,
it's pretty clear what
safety means here.
These ratings for
safety ratings for cars,
which involve testing
based on smashing cars
into a wall with an
airbag and seeing
how well it does and protects
the dummies in the car.
And this is with decades of
lobbying and figuring out
what safety means for vehicles.
So what does it mean for AI?
So I would say that there
is not a great answer here,
but I'll give you some
examples of what people
have been thinking about.
So there's this benchmark
called Harm-Bench.
And this is really about
prompting a model with things
that are meant to be harmful
and expecting the model
to essentially refuse.
So this is one type of safety.
And I think probably
the dominant thing
when people think
about safety is
that I want to prevent bad
actors from doing things
with language models,
but it turns out
that's not the only
thing that matters.
So there's this other
work, AIR-Bench,
which tries to think
about safety holistically
by looking at all the regulatory
frameworks in the EU, China,
and the US company
policies and builds
a taxonomy of all the different
things that could go wrong.
And then using
this, constructing
a particular set of
prompts and evaluating
and so on and so forth.
But one problem with
safety is, jailbreaking,
which is its own
sub problem, which
is that language models
are generally trained
to refuse harmful instructions.
But as we know you can get
around this if you're clever.
And so there's some
early work that
uses automatic ways to optimize
for prompts to bypass safety
using GCG, which is
basically this coordinate
wise optimization algorithm.
And remarkably,
optimizing on open models
allows us to transfer to models.
So I hope this doesn't these
attacks don't work anymore.
But at the time, you can
generate some basically
gibberish and step by step
plan to destroy humanity
and OpenAI's model will comply.
Obviously, you
could argue, well,
is this actually harmful
plan to destroy humanity?
At least it did not-- the
expected behavior is that it
should probably refuse that.
So this raises a bigger problem
which is, what is safety?
And one thing that
makes this tricky
is that many aspects of
safety are very contextual.
So it involves politics,
law, social norms.
This varies across
different countries.
And then also, if you
think about safety,
you have to think about
what are the risks.
And the risks are actually
quite varied as well
and demand probably
different attention.
So hallucinations is
a risk, especially
let's say a medical or
legal or financial settings.
But this is also correlated
with just capabilities.
If you make a model
more accurate,
it's correlated with not
who is seeing as much.
Sycophancy is a problem.
Abetting crimes is a problem.
But this might be counter
to capabilities, inequality.
Losing critical thinking might
be a risk as well that correlate
with capability.
So if you think about the
societal impact of language
models on the world
and think about safety
as ensuring that AI
goes well for people,
this is actually a
much more complex topic
than I'll have
time to talk about.
And finally, there is a dual
use aspect of language models.
So the cybersecurity agents can
be used to hack into a system
or to do penetration testing and
make systems more secure, which
makes talking about whether
these are safety risks
or actually beneficial
a double-edged sword.
OK, so let's move on now
to talk about some broader
considerations of evaluation.
So one thing that I think is an
important aspect of evaluation
is realism or
ecological validity.
How well does evaluation
capture real-world use?
So in particular exams are very
far away from real-world use.
Chatbot Arena are
from real people
but one could wonder
whether this distribution is
the right distribution of
people or use cases or not.
There's a few
benchmarks I'll mention
that try to get at
ecological validity,
and in particular at
the use case level,
at least not the
individual query level.
So OpenAI created
benchmark called GDPVal.
They looked at all
the top nine sectors
according to US GDP, 44
different occupations,
got a bunch of professionals
to create tasks.
These are professionals with
about 14 years of experience.
And you can see people who
are nurses who work concierge,
real estate agents,
film and video editors
and so on and so forth.
And they created
a bunch of tasks.
Here's another example.
In the medical domain
where up until this point,
a lot of medical benchmarks were
based on standardized exams.
And in fact,
actually for humans,
this is also what happens.
You take these
standardized exams
and you graduate from med school
and then you go operate on.
Well, actually, there's
a longer process.
You don't operate on
patients directly.
But the point is that
for a language model,
you should also not
just pass medical exams
and deploy them directly.
So this was a project
where 121 tasks were
sourced from 29 clinicians.
And this was meant to
represent the type of things
that clinicians would actually
ask to a language model, which
are quite different
than the multiple choice
type of exam questions.
Here's another project
which gets at real data.
So if you ask, who
actually has the data
on what people are doing?
Well, it's the model developers.
And so this project
is interesting
because it uses language models
themselves to analyze real data.
So in particular,
you do to privacy.
You can't literally go
and look at people's data,
but you can have language
models look at the data
and analyze and summarize
general patterns.
So then the language
models could tell you
about what are the
types of people--
what are the types of things
that people use Claude for?
And sometimes
realism and privacy
are at odds with each
other because ideally you
would want actually a sample
from the actual query stream.
And that would be very
valuable to assess
how well a model is working
and understand deeply
what the errors are.
But then that runs into
privacy considerations.
OK, so another
consideration, which
is another type of validity
is just in general,
how do that the evaluations
are scientifically valid?
And this was brought up fairly
early, train-test overlap
or contamination.
So in a machine
learning 101, you
learn don't train on
your test set hopefully.
And before foundation
models this
was actually pretty clear right.
So with ImageNet and
SQuAD and many benchmarks
sorry, data sets, there
was always a train split
and a test split and everyone
played the same game.
You train on your training data,
you test on your test data.
Life was simple.
And now, you have
these models that
are trained on the internet.
And much more than that.
And furthermore, you
don't what's in the data.
So this makes evaluation
quite different I think.
So what can you do in this?
So first thing you
can do is you can
try to infer whether a model
has actually seen the test data.
So this is a neat idea
from Tatsu's group
where you leverage the
fact that the order
in which the questions
in the benchmark occurs
should be random.
But if the model prefers
some particular order that's
consistent with the
benchmark, that is probably--
it's just trained
on that benchmark.
Another route is that you can
encourage people to report
actual train-test overlap.
So this has to do with norms.
I think in general, especially
maybe less in machine learning,
but more in
statistics you always
report confidence intervals.
You have an estimate.
And I always want to know,
how reliable is that estimate?
This is just standard practice.
And so the idea of
this position paper
is that you should
model providers.
If you're going to
claim some GPQA score,
you should always provide
some justification
that you didn't train
on the test set.
So another route is that
where you can just give up.
It's like OK, all these
evaluations there--
let's just assume that
people trained on them, let's
assume the worst case.
So the thing that
we have on our side
is that you can always
define fresh evals.
So there's a bunch of ideas,
LiveCodeBench, UncheeatableEval,
which basically scrape
new web pages or archive
papers or GitHub and defines
evaluations populations that
are past the cutoff date
of the language models.
So this seems pretty
robust and good.
But one thing to keep in
mind is that time stamps
aren't always safe
either, because I might
post with code for example.
I might put something on
GitHub which is actually
derived from some other repo.
And so how do that's
actually generally fresh?
Route 4 is to use
private evaluations.
So companies' model
developers do this right.
So if you're Google or OpenAI
you have your internal code
base, which you assume
is not on the internet,
and you obviously wouldn't
train on this data,
so you can use it
for evaluation.
So this generally
is pretty reliable.
And if you're not a company, you
can use your personal writings.
I have a bunch of
rejected papers from when
I was in grad school that
I never put on online,
so I can use those.
And this type of
evaluation, I think,
is very favorable
for perplexity evals,
because all you
need in perplexity
is just you need a
good data set and you
can evaluate log probabilities.
So another concern that I'll
mention is data set quality.
So remember I showed
the leaderboard
for SWE-Bench Verified.
This is because,
well, SWE-Bench had
a bunch of problems of
tasks, unit tests that
weren't quite rigorous enough
and other things that got fixed.
And there are many other
benchmarks that have gone
through this process
like GSM8K or MMLU,
where people have gone and done
a more careful audit and realize
that, wait a minute, this
question actually doesn't--
something's broken
around this question.
So like this one.
There's no curve
given in this text
so you can't answer
this question.
Does the baby have socks on?
No, there's no way to tell.
And there's also this paper
that showed that there's
a lot of problems with the
agentic benchmarks, which
arguably are even harder to
assess because it's not just
you can look at the question
and the possible answers
and you can look at it but
there's a whole environment.
And there are cases
where with coding you can
it's great to have test cases
that either pass or not passed.
But as we all test
cases can be incomplete.
So you might pass
all the test cases
but still not have
a working solution.
There's another case of
this TorchBench benchmark
where they show that if an agent
just outputs the empty response,
they can get a 38%.
So there are some trivialities
with these benchmarks
that you want have to be
very careful to avoid.
One thing I'll call
out is that there's
this tool called
Docent that uses
language models to inspect
agent traces to detect problems.
So this is a
qualitative response
to our very quantitative
heavy way of benchmarking.
And I would always
recommend that whenever
you do a benchmark,
either develop a benchmark
or run a model on the
benchmark that you always
look at the output and try
to audit it to make sure
that you actually think
you're measuring what
you think you're measuring.
OK, so maybe getting a
bit more philosophical.
So what's the point
of evaluation?
OK.
So I've talked a lot about
different types of evaluation.
And really, there's no one
evaluation to rule them all.
And I think it's-- when you're
thinking about evaluation,
you have to be very clear
about what the purpose is.
And I think often this is
not really stated clearly.
So for example, you
could be a user,
or a company that's trying
to make a purchase decision.
Are you going to go with A or
B for a particular use case?
Or you're just a
researcher and you
have this intuitive
notion of intelligence
and you want to
measure it somehow.
Or you want to understand the
benefits and harms for business
or policy reasons.
Or you're a developer and
you want to get feedback
to improve the model.
So each of these
goals will lead you
to potentially different
benchmarks or some combination
of evaluation strategies.
And finally, one
thing to address,
which I hinted at
briefly, is that
what are we even evaluating?
So before foundation models,
researchers evaluated methods
because we have these
trained test splits.
And the only thing that was
varying is the actual algorithm.
And today, we're mostly
evaluating models and systems
where anything goes.
There are some exceptions.
So the NanoGPT speedrun
is deliberately
a way to evaluate an algorithm,
in particular, how well fast you
can train a model.
But most of language
model evaluation
is about evaluating the actual
end model, which is useful
because that is the thing that
is actually going to get shipped
and people are going to use.
But I think the punchline
is that you should always
be very deliberate about
declaring what your goals are.
OK, so there's no
one true evaluation.
Choose what you're
trying to measure.
And we talked about a bunch
of different benchmarks
starting with perplexity, exam
based, chat, agentic, reasoning,
and safety.
They vary in terms of
difficulty, realism,
how valid they are.
And there's often trade offs.
It's hard to have really real
and difficult and ecologically
valid.
And no trade tests
contamination.
So often you have to compromise
on one of these factors,
and depending on
your goals, you will
have to choose which one you're
willing to compromise on.
So that is the end
of this lecture.
So next week, we're
going to start
talking about training data.
OK, see you next time.
[AUDIO LOGO]